Okay בוקר טוב *Boker Tov* to
fix the way the mic is it looks like
it's pointing your shirt sideways I don't know what that
okay בוקר טוב *Boker Tov* today's
דף *Daf* is דף כ"א *Daf
Chaf Alef* in
סנהדרין
*Sanhedrin*.
We're going to pick up on כ' עמוד ב' *Chaf Amud Bet*
a really kind of I don't know how many call it 15
lines from the bottom.
We're just talking about the order of the three things they needed
to do when they went into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, *Eretz Yisrael*
it was to have a מלך melech *Melech* then to wipe out
עמלק *Amalek* and then to build the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*.
So we're up to אמר ריש לקיש *Amar Reish Lakish* בתחילה מלך
שלמה Shlomo, על עליונים *Batichila malach Shlomo al elyonim*. It's right well
depending on what version of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* you have there's
a ליקוטי רש"י *Likutey Rashi* it's right over there. Do you have
the place David? Okay. So
in the beginning שלמה Solomon, *Shlomo* was king even over you know
the heavens like meaning the celestial sphere like the angels demons those
kind of things שנאמר shene'emar, וישב שלמה Shlomo על כיסא ה' *shenemar
Vayeshev Shlomo al kisei Hashem*. So he was on the כיסא *Kisei*
of ה' *Hashem* even so you know God was in a totally
different sphere up in the heavens. ולבסוף מלך על תחתונים *U-levasof malach
al tachtonim* in the end he only had
dominion in our temporal world our you know current
physical
world שנאמר shenemar כי הוא רדה בכל עבר הנהר מתפסח ועד עזה
*shenemar Ki hu rodeh bechol ever hanahar mi-Tifsach ve-ad Azah*. So he
was you know ruling over the entire עבר הנהר *ever hanahar* from
these two places תפסח *Tifsach* and עזה *Azah*. רב Rav ושמואל *Rav
u-Shmuel* basically going to say the same point but get to it
differently. חדא אמר *Chada amar* תפסח *Tifsach* סוף עולם *sofa olam* ועזה
*ve-Azah* סוף עולם *sofa olam*. They're like you know 180 degrees from
each other. וחדא אמר *Ve-chada amar* תפסח ועזה בהדי הדדי הוו יתבי
*Tifsach ve-Azah bahadei hadadi havu yatevei*.
And they were right next to each other but כשם שמלך על
תפסח ועל עזה כך מלך על כל העולם כולו *keshem shemalach al
Tifsach ve-al Azah kach malach al kol ha-olam kulo*.
And it's so too he was king over the entire world. Or
you can just say like you know people around the other way
you know then you get the whole world which is the same
thing like מהודו ועד כוש *me-Hodu ve-ad Kush*. Like that's what they
say like one was here one was there or they were right
next to each other and you get everything you know around.
Anyway at some point he was king over the heavenly and the
earthly worlds. ולבסוף מלך אלא על ישראל *U-levasof malach ela al
Yisrael*. So in the end it was only just the kingdom of
ישראל *Yisrael* שנאמר אני קהלת הייתי מלך על ישראל *shenemar Ani Kohelet
hayiti melech al Yisrael*. And then the next one is בירושלים *bi-Yerushalayim*.
ולבסוף מלך אלא על ירושלים Yerushalayim, *U-levasof malach ela al Yerushalayim*. So
it sort of was getting gradually smaller. And then later on it
was only on ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim* שנאמר דברי קהלת בן דוד David
מלך בירושלים *shenemar Divrei Kohelet ben David melech bi-Yerushalayim* where's קהלת *Kohelet*
the son of David the king of ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim* or saying
קהלת *Kohelet* is שלמה Shlomo *Shlomo*. ולבסוף מלך אלא על מיטתו *U-levasof
malach ela al mitato*. And in the end all he had was
his own bed שנאמר הנה מיטתו שלשלמה *shenemar Hinei mitato sheli-Shlomo* the
מיטתו *mitato* of שלמה Shlomo *Shlomo*. ולבסוף מלך אלא על מקלו *U-levasof
malach ela al maklo*. And in the end all he had he
didn't even have that all he had was his staff שנאמר זה
היה חלקי מכל עמלי *shenemar Ze hayah chelki mikol amali* this is
all I had from
whatever
I had. And I don't know how you get that that means
his staff but you know me from something זה *ze* like something
you can like show pretty easily so his מקל *makel*. רב Rav
ושמואל *Rav
u-Shmuel* when you say זה *ze* חדא אמר מקלו וחדא אמר גונדו
*chada amar maklo ve-chada amar gundo*. One said that it was his
מקלו *maklo* the other said it was like his cloak so you
know you really have like nothing.
So there was a you know and so the reason why did
that happen I think it had to do with like a story
of אשמדאי *Ashmedai* like you know the king of the demons and
you know sort of like he got into a little bit of
trouble with him and then אשמדאי *Ashmedai* took his crown and you
know assumed his form and all that. Interesting right
yeah so anyway yeah they say that here too in the
note and I remember that from גיטין *Gittin*. Okay anyway
I was just trying to see how they just get it from
the word זה *ze* but you know I think it might be
as I said.
Okay.
So was this a temporary thing was this a permanent thing הדר
לא
הדר *Hadar lo hadar*. Did he you know regain his former glory
to at least be king you know over more than just his
staff? You know how much how far are we saying did he
you know was he king over like all the world again and
the heavenly spheres or just ישראל *Yisrael*? I don't know. רב ושמואל
חדא אמר הדר וחדא אמר לא הדר *Rav u-Shmuel chada amar hadar
ve-chada amar lo hadar*. One said he yeah he became king again
the other says not really. מאן דאמר לא הדר *Man de-amar lo
hadar* מלך והדיוט *malach ve-hediyot*. He was a king and then you
know became like a commoner. מאן דאמר הדר *Man de-amar hadar* obviously
מלך והדיוט ומלך *malach ve-hediyot u-malach*. He became a king then yeah
kind of got demoted and then regained it. Okay and we talked
about the king can sort of you know
ram through things in order to make a road. Way for himself,
people's houses, people's vineyards, that kind of thing.
Then they talked about as well he gets the choice
spoils, how much does he get? תנו רבנן, אוצרות מלכים, otzrot melachim,
למלך, lemelech, ושאר ביזה שבוזזין, veshear biza shebozezin, מחצה למלך ומחצה לעם.
mechetza lemelech umechetza la'am. So
there are different kinds of spoils. So there's like the king's, if
you conquer another province, there's the king's treasure house and then there's
like the rest of everything.
So one says, okay, the king's treasure house goes to the king,
that makes sense. And the rest of it, that's split equally between
the king and the nation. So it's good to be king, you
get quite a lot.
If you're the winning king.
Yeah. Right, true. אמר ליה אביי לרב דימי ואמרי לה לרב אחא,
amar lei Abaye leRav Dimi ve'amri la leRav Acha, בשלמא אוצרות מלכים
למלך אורחא דמילתא היא. bishlama otzrot melachim lemelech orcha demilta hi.
So
we understand that why the king should get the other king's treasures
because that's, you know, that's kind of way it goes, אלא שאר
ביזה שבוזזין מחצה למלך ומחצה לעם מנא לן? ela shear biza shebozezin
mechetza lemelech umechetza la'am mena lan? So how do we know that
even the rest of everything, the king gets half of that too?
So שנאמר, דכתיב, dechtiv, וימשחו לה' לנגיד ולצדוק לכהן, vayimshchu l'Hashem lenagid
uletzadok lechohen, something like that. Yeah, ולצדוק לכהן. uletzadok lechohen.
So they compare in one, at one time, so they,
which is interesting, that's from a פסוק, pasuk, וימליכו שנית לשלמה, vayamlichu
shenit li'Shlomo, which might sound like, you know, he became king again,
echoing our previous conversation. But anyway, so they reinaugurated Shlomo to be,
and it's obviously to be a king and then they also made
צדוק Tzadok to be the כהן. kohen. So מקיש נגיד לצדוק, makish
nagid letzadok, they compare the king to the כהן, kohen, מה צדוק
מחצה לו ומחצה לאחיו, ma Tzadok mechetza lo umechetza le'achiv, just like
the כהן kohen gets half of stuff, which we'll talk about that
in a second, so too the king gets half of stuff. וצדוק
גופיה מנא לן? veTzadok gufei mena lan? How do we know that
the כהן kohen gets half the stuff? דתניא רבי אומר והיתה לאהרן
ולבניו מחצה לאהרן ומחצה לבניו. detanya Rabi omer vehayta le'Aharon ulevanav mechetza
le'Aharon umechetza levanav. When it talks about the לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim,
it says that that should be לאהרן ולבניו. le'Aharon ulevanav. So it
could just mean that we're just talking about the כהנים, kohanim, right?
But we're saying no, אהרן Aharon gets half and then his children
get half. And then we abstract that to mean like sort of
everything. You know, by the way, there was, I think it would
be an interesting parallel, when the in מטות, Matot, there is the
war against מדין, Midyan, והרמת מכס לה' אחד נפש מחמש המאות, vaharimta
meches l'Hashem echad nefesh mechamesh hame'ot, like,
you know, but we don't say that exactly. You know, we say
מחצה. mechetza. It would depending on who it was, there were the
fighters and then there was the rest of the nation. So, you
know, it was split. And then from the fighters, they had to
give like a little, you know, a little less since they're the
ones that like did everything. I think it's one out of 500.
Do you have a חומש chumash there? At the end? במטות? beMatot?
Yeah.
So,
yeah, the fighters got to keep more.
So, over there it was,
right, so you know the booty was split
between
the fighters and everyone else. And then the fighters have to give
up what I thought like, you know, one out of 500,
and that was given to אלעזר. Elazar.
And from the rest of the people, one out of 50.
So yeah, now again there was no king at the time, and
then it was given to יהושע, Yehoshua, but, you know, but it's
still interesting that it really it certainly wasn't half, you know. So
I guess, you know, things changed. I don't know. But anyway, biblical
precedent is not helping with
this to learn this from that. All right, anyway, so that's what
we end up saying that so the king gets the treasure house
of the king whom they deposed, you know, who they won and
beat, defeated in the war, and he also gets half of everything
else. לא ירבה לו נשים אלא שמונה עשרה. lo yarbe lo nashim
ela shmona esrei. So
he can't have too many wives, he can have 18. רבי יהודה
אומר מרבה הוא לו ובלבד שלא יהיו מסירות לבו. Rabi Yehuda omer
marbe hu lo u'vilvad shelo yehu mesirot libo. No, he can have
more, but as long as they don't turn his heart astray. 'Cause
it says, that was the whole point in the פסוק pasuk
that לא ירבה לו נשים ולא יסור לבבו, lo yarbe lo nashim
velo yasur levavo, and also רק לא ירבה לו סוסים, rak lo
yarbe lo susim, I'm just blanking on a פסוק pasuk for a
minute.
Here it is,
לא ירבה לו נשים ולא יסור לבבו וכסף וזהב לא ירבה לו
מאד. lo yarbe lo nashim velo yasur levavo vechesef vezahav lo yarbe
lo me'od. So that that was one. And then there's like another
one that talks about the, you know, going more to get. horses.
And that פסוק pasuk which we're going to quote also,
have it right here anyway so might as well open up to
it.
It's all on the same פרשה parsha
which is also again what we were talking about before having to
set a kingdom up. He has to have a ספר תורה sefer
Torah and we're going to talk about all that now anyway, so
I might as well just read that whole פסוק. pasuk. So when
you're going to come into ארץ ישראל, the land that God will
give you and you're going to say אשים עלי מלך ככל הגוים
אשר סביבותי, asim alai melech kechol hagoyim asher svivotai, let me have
a מלך like all the גוים אשר סביבותי, goyim asher svivotai, which
is interesting because remember we were talking about before that the זקנים
zkenim
שאלו כהוגן, sha'alu kahogen, they said we want to be judged, and
the commoners did not ask nicely because they said ככל הגוים. kechol
hagoyim. Interestingly, the Torah here says ככל הגוים. kechol hagoyim. So, you
know, so just
something
to think about
and then, which may prompt people to say that which is a
מחלוקת, machloket, like, you know, should you be having a king or
should you really not? You know, is it sort of ideal? שמואל
Shmuel obviously thought it wasn't, right, which is why you had that
whole thing. But God said it's okay. So anyway, he's supposed to
שום תשים עליך מלך, som tasim alecha melech, he should place upon
yourself a king and that's what we said שום תשים שתהא אימתו
עליך, som tasim she'tehei eimato alecha, to place him over you, has
to be so you have to kind of view him as, you
know, over you at all times, you have to live in fear
of him so to speak. Not fear of him, but you know,
you have to view him with a certain amount of respect and
fear
too that you know, you just can't act so lightly in front
of him. מקרב אחיך תשים עליך מלך, mikerev achecha tasim alecha melech,
he has to be from your brethren. לא תוכל לתת עליך איש
נכרי אשר לא אחיך הוא, lo tuchal latet alecha ish nochri asher
lo achecha hu, he can't be a foreigner, which is the whole
problem with like הורדוס Hordus and if you remember like, you know,
he was a slave, you know, how could he be a king?
And they said no, you are our brother and then they said
the sages at the time got punished because they were sort of
they were מחניף, machnif, they were, I don't know what a good
translation of that is, but they were, you know, flattering הורדוס Hordus
when they shouldn't have. And then רק לא ירבה לו סוסים, rak
lo yarbeh lo susim, so he can't have horses, too many horses.
ולא ישיב את העם מצרימה למען הרבות סוס v'lo yashiv et ha'am
mitzraima l'ma'an harbot sus and he shouldn't bring back the people to
מצרים Mitzrayim in order to get these horses. וה' אמר לכם לא
תסיפון לשוב בדרך הזה עוד, v'Adonai amar lachem lo tosifun lashuv baderech
hazeh od, and God said you can't come back this way. ולא
ירבה לו נשים ולא יסור לבבו, v'lo yarbeh lo nashim v'lo yasur
levavo, he should not have too many wives and his heart should
not be led astray. וכסף וזהב לא ירבה לו מאד v'chesef v'zahav
lo yarbeh lo me'od and he should not have too many, too
much money. So by the סוסים, susim, you might say that the
reason why he shouldn't have too many סוסים susim is in order
not to bring the nation back to Egypt, right? Or you could
say they're two separate things. He can't have too many horses and
he can't bring back, and a separate, a separate prohibition on top
of that is, you know, to be even worse if he took
the nation back to Egypt to get סוסים. susim. And then it
says also by the women, gives a reason, right? That he can't
have too many women and ולא יסור לבבו, v'lo yasur levavo, so
that they should not turn his heart astray. But by כסף וזהב,
chesef v'zahav, it just says לא ירבה לו מאד, lo yarbeh lo
me'od, it doesn't say why, right? Just says he just can't have
any. So it doesn't say, oh well it's because of this reason.
Presumably because it's kind of self-understood, you know, why he shouldn't. And
then, and we're going to talk about this too, והיה כשבתו על
כסא ממלכתו, v'haya k'shivto al kisei mamlachto, when he will be seated
on his throne, וכתב לו את משנה התורה הזאת, v'chatav lo et
mishneh hatorah hazot, he needs to write this משנה תורה הזאת mishneh
hatorah hazot על ספר מלפני הכהנים הלוים. al sefer milifnei hakohanim haleviyim.
So what does that mean? So what's משנה התורה הזאת? mishneh hatorah
hazot? Is it literally משנה תורה, Mishneh Torah, דברים? Devarim? Some people
say that. Or is it all the תורה? Torah? And what does
משנה תורה mishneh torah mean? You know, like how many ספרי תורה
sifrei torah does he have to have? We're going to get into
all that. That's what's, sort of why I read these פסוקים psukim
and that is the basis of what we're going to be talking
about. דברים יז? Devarim yod zayin?
Yes. It's שופטים, Shoftim, יז יד. yod zayin yud dalet. Yeah, it
starts from פסוק יד, pasuk yud dalet, 14. Okay. 17:14.
Okay, so he can only have 18. רבי יהודה אומר ירבה לו
ובלבד שלא יהיו מסירות את לבו. Rabbi Yehuda omer yarbeh lo u'vilvad
shelo yehu mesirot et libo. Rabbi Yehuda says he can have it,
just that, you know, so long as they don't turn his heart
astray, which is what the Torah said,
don't do that to have your heart turned astray.
רבי שמעון אומר אפילו אחת ומסירה את לבו הרי זו לא ישאנה.
Rabbi Shimon omer afilu achat u'mesira et libo harei zu lo yisa'ena.
No, even one, if she's going to turn his heart astray, he
shouldn't marry her. אם כן למה נאמר ולא ירבה לו נשים? im
ken lama ne'emar v'lo yarbeh lo nashim? The Torah seems to say
that it's not just a question of one. Seems to be that
there's, you know, that there's a lot,
that having a lot is the problem. And Rabbi Shimon is saying
even one could be a problem, so what do we learn from
not having too many? דאפילו כאביגיל, d'afilu k'Avigail, even if they're all
like very righteous, he still can't have too many. So he can,
yeah, one, a bad one you can't marry at all, but even
good ones you can't have more than 18. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says no, he can have as many as he wants as long
as they're not going to turn his heart astray. למימרא דרבי יהודה
דריש טעמא דקרא ורבי שמעון לא דריש טעמא דקרא? leimeira d'Rabbi Yehuda
darish ta'ama d'kra v'Rabbi Shimon lo darish ta'ama d'kra? Do we say
that since Rabbi Yehuda is saying, oh, I understand the reason,
and the... for the reason leads me to say, such and such,
that he is looking at the that he looks at the reason
behind things and then is willing to interpret the פסוקים psukim in
line with the reason which may lead to somewhat different conclusions than
the פסוקים psukim are trying to say, as opposed to
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says no, the cutoff is a certain
amount, whatever we say that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda means, but that
is it, right? He is not saying the reason is because they
will turn his heart astray and therefore maybe he can have more.
But so is that the party lines of the מחלוקת? machloket? But
usually we say the opposite.
We know that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is a very big guy
who is דריש טעמא דקרא. darish tama dekra. דתניא De-tanya אלמנה, almana,
בין שהיא עניה בין שהיא עשירה, bein shehi aniya bein shehi ashira,
אין ממשכנין אותה. ein memashkenin otah. It says לא תחבול בגד אלמנה.
lo tachbol beged almana. So you cannot take the cloak basically you
cannot take a collateral from an אלמנה. almana. So what would be
the reason
and to what does that apply?
Because usually the widow, the orphan, they are the poor ones in
society, right? So you do not want to be taking their stuff
so let
us say she is a rich widow. She does not need
this particular cloak today. She is not going to need it at
all because she has one for every day of the year. So
then can you take it? So we say that the reason is
that you are looking at really what you think the טעמא דקרא
tama dekra is because then she is poor, she cannot afford it,
but we are going to say it is a different reason. But
anyway, let us go with the poor thing. So if we say
the reason is that you cannot take it because she is poor
and that would be unfair to her, then if she is rich
you can take it. That is what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says,
that if she is rich you can take it.
And but others would say no, you cannot take it, that is
just saying no, I do not care about any possible
reasons, the Torah says so. So that seems to be the opposite.
Over here, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in the case of the king
is saying I do not care how many I do not care
what the reason is, he just cannot have too many, right? But
over there in the case of the אלמנה, almana, he is saying
the reason is leading me to say that if she is a
rich one you actually can take something from her. So it seems
to be that he is changing his position. אלמנה almana בין שהיא
עניה בין שהיא עשירה bein shehi aniya bein shehi ashira אין ממשכנין
אותה ein memashkenin otah whether she is rich or poor you cannot
you cannot take a collateral from her שנאמר ולא תחבול בגד אלמנה
velo tachbol beged almana דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says you just cannot take it, that is just the
end of it. רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon omer עשירה ממשכנין אותה
ashira memashkenin otah עניה אין ממשכנין אותה. aniya ein memashkenin otah.
A rich one you can, a poor one you cannot,
ואתה חייב להחזיר לה veata chayav lehachazir lah ואתה משיא שם רע
בשכנותיה. veata mashia shem ra bishchenoteha. And you have to give it
back to her and then you will have her have a bad
name amongst her neighbors. What do you mean but you cannot take
it but you have to give it back and then she gets
a what what is all that? So he explains אם כן מאי
קאמר הכי קאמר im ken mai kaamar hachi kaamar מתוך שאתה ממשכנה,
mitokh sheata memashkenah, if you are going to take
a משכון mashkon then if she is poor, ואתה חייב להחזיר לה,
veata chayav lehachazir lah, she is going to need it, right? So
if she is going to need it, she is going to come
to you. And if she comes to you, you are going to
have to give it back to her. And then ואתה משיא שם
רע
בשכנותיה. veata mashia shem ra bishchenoteha. And then she is going to
have a bad name oh look she is going to that guy
all the time. What is she going to that guy all the
time for? Must be they are doing something inappropriate. And they are
not going to realize she is just getting back
her whatever it is. So
that is why. So he says okay then therefore to avoid all
that and do not take anything from her at all if she
is poor. But if she is rich she is not going to
come back to you because she is not going to need it,
so she is not going to get a bad name. So אמר
יהודה לא דריש טעמא דקרא amar Yehuda lo darish tama dekra ורבי
שמעון דריש טעמא דקרא. veRabbi Shimon darish tama dekra. So we see
that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is willing to look at the reason
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is not. But over here in the
king case, it seems to be just the opposite.
So we say how do you reconcile that? So we answer ואמר
רבי יהודה לא דריש טעמא דקרא. veamar Rabbi Yehuda lo darish tama
dekra. So the default is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is not דריש
טעמא דקרא darish tama dekra and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is. So
why is this different with the king? שאני הכא shani hacha דמפרש
טעמא דקרא demefaresh tama dekra מאי טעמא לא ירבה mai tama lo
yarbeh לו נשים משום ולא יסור לבבו. The Torah is really very
explicit as to what the reason is. In the case of the
אלמנה almana it does not actually say what the reason is it
does not give a reason, just says לא תחבול בגד אלמנה. lo
tachbol beged almana.
So then רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is looking to see what he
thinks the reason would be and is willing to operate based on
that. But over here there is an explicit reason. So it is
kind of hard to say not דריש טעמא דקרא. darish tama dekra.
So given what the reason seems to be, that is what רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. Okay, well the reason is turning his heart
astray so I am willing to say that
having too many turning his heart astray is a problem.
But until that point it is okay. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon אמר
לך amar lach מכדי mikdei בעלמא bealma דרשינן darshinan טעמא דקרא tama
dekra I do usually דרוש darish the טעמא דקרא. tama dekra. So
and if so, אם כן לכתוב קרא im ken lichtov kra לא
ירבה לו נשים ולשתוק. lo yarbeh lo nashim velishtok.
Just in the case of בגד אלמנה beged almana the Torah did
not give a reason, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon partially did the reason.
So too in this case he would have partially did a reason
too why not to have too many wives. So the Torah did
not actually even need to give a reason. So the fact that
it went out of its way to give a reason, the Torah
could have just been quiet about it. ואנא אמינא veana amina מאי
טעמא mai tama לא ירבה lo yarbeh? משום דלא יסור. mishum delo
yasur. So I would have known that that was the reason. So
ולא יסור למה לי? velo yasur lama li? So why did the
Torah have to be very explicit about it? So therefore I learn
אפילו אחת ומסירה את לבו. afilu achat umesirah et libo. and it's
to tell you that it doesn't make a difference how many it
is. You can't have too many anyway. And even one that will
turn his heart astray, which rather seems to make sense. I mean,
you shouldn't marry a bad person, right? הרי זה לא ישאנה. harei
zeh lo yisanna. So אלא מאי אני מקיים לא
ירבה? ella mai ani mikayem lo yarbeh? So if I would have
known that it's a problem of turning his heart astray and even
one would be a problem, why do I need the פסוק pasuk
then to tell you לא ירבה? So אפילו כאביגיל, afilu k'Avigayil, then
no matter how many, no matter how righteous, having too many would
be a problem.
Okay, so that's the base of their מחלוקת. machloket. And we said
having too many's 18. שמונה עשר מנא לן? shmoneh asar m'na lan?
How do we know that you get 18? דכתיב, dechativ, and this
is a פסוק pasuk I quoted yesterday which is why I was
doing all this, ויולדו לדוד בנים בחברון ויהי בכורו אמנון Amnon לאחינועם
היזרעאלית ומשנהו כלאב לאביגיל אשת נבל הכרמלי 2 והשלישי אבשלום Avshalom בן
מעכה 3 והרביעי אדוניה Adoniya בן חגית 4 והחמישי שפטיה בן אביטל
5 והששי יתרעם Yitream, לעגלה אשת דוד David אלה ילדו לדוד
בחברון.
So these were the ones that were born to דוד David in
חברון. Chevron. That is שמואל ב' ג'. Shmuel Bet Gimmel. And
then much later on then
you have a whole thing with דוד David taking,
who was the one woman he really did a big sin taking,
well the two, but
I'm sorry? בת שבע. Batsheva. Right. So בת שבע Batsheva was a
really big problem.
And what happened? So there's this very famous parable that, so he
took בת שבע, Batsheva, he basically had אוריה Uriah killed off. And
that was the reason he did that really was because
it seems from, look, אוריה Uriah was one of his גיבורים. gibborim.
He was one of his mighty men anyway, would have been in
the front. But he really wanted to work it such, he had
everyone step back to have אוריה Uriah really the center of the
enemy's attacks and they killed him. And then he took בת שבע.
Batsheva. And then
נתן הנביא Natan HaNavi comes and gives him this very famous parable
of
the
sheep. There was a rich man and a poor man,
they were neighbors with each other. And then the rich man had
some guests over. He's like,
"I don't want to kill my stuff." So he took the one
sheep of the poor person that was much loved by them and
he killed it off. And then דוד David gets furious and says,
"That guy needs to pay back many many many times and he
should be killed." So then נתן Natan says, "Yeah, you're that guy.
אוריה Uriah had this one wife, you have all these other
wives," and ואם מעט, v'im m'at, and this is what we're going
to quote, ואסיפה לך כהנה וכהנה. v'osifa lach kahena v'kahena. And if
that was even too much for you, God would have given you
more. So what are you doing taking a married woman?
Then he says
חטאתי. chatati. דוד Dovid says חטאתי. chatati. And in that whole passage,
by the way, the נביא navi says you're going to have a
whole bunch of things. הנני מקים עליך רעה
מתוך ביתך.
hineni mekim alecha
ra'ah mitoch beitecha. You're going to have an evil from your house.
And we had that whole
thing that he's going to do all these terrible things are going
to happen. He's going to do all that and that'll be like
the end of you, basically. He says חטאתי. chatati. So נתן Natan
says, "Alright, גם ה'
העביר חטאתך לא תמות." gam Hashem he'evir chatatcha lo tamut. God forgive
your sin. But the son that you have from this will die.
And that's what happened. So
anyway...
But then Solomon came
from Bathsheba.
Solomon
came and right.
And it's important to realize, and we're not going to quote this,
is that it talks about the different children that דוד Dovid had
and one of them was שלמה, which was mentioned like way back
before this. And then you have this פסוק pasuk ואם מעט ואסיפה
לך כהנה וכהנה. v'im m'at v'osifa lach kahena v'kahena. And this was
the same פסוק pasuk we're quoting, by the way, to quote the
whole פסוק, pasuk, it's ואתנה לך את בית אדוניך ואת נשי אדוניך
בחיקך. va'etna l'cha et beit adonecha v'et neshei adonecha b'cheikecha. God had
given you all this. The house of your
master which was basically שאול, Shaul, which he did. He became the
king. ונשי אדוניך בחיקך. v'neshei adonecha b'cheikecha. And the wives of your
master or the women of your master, which the גמרא Gemara interpreted
to mean women which were his two daughters. ואתנה לך את בית
ישראל
ויהודה. va'etna l'cha et beit Yisrael v'Yehuda. And also all בית ישראל
Beit Yisrael and יהודה, Yehuda, meaning he'll be king over everybody. ואם
מעט ואסיפה לך כהנה וכהנה. v'im m'at v'osifa lach kahena v'kahena. And
if that would have been too little, God would have given you
here more, here and more there. Maybe more other
kingdoms because they did conquer a bunch, or more women, the גמרא
Gemara is taking that to mean more wives. So the question was,
how do you get to 18?
So we said that that's שמואל ב'? Shmuel Bet?
That is
שמואל, Shmuel, yeah well we're going a whole bunch of things.
The six that he had was earlier, it's the beginning of שמואל
ב', Shmuel Bet, that's פרק ג'. Perek Gimmel. The
one we had after that,
כהנה וכהנה, kahena v'kahena, that's like ten פרקים prakim later. Right.
A lot went on between them. You know, like that whole thing
with בת שבע Bat Sheva, *Batsheva*, like I was mentioning.
And it also mentioned that he had a whole that and everything
I was reading yesterday about איש בושת *Ish-Bosheth* and that אבנר *Abner*
was מלך *molech* איש בושת *Ish-Bosheth*. All that, all that happened. And
then the whole thing about אבנר *Abner* being killed off and דוד
David *David* having making this קינה *kina*, then everyone finally understood
that דוד David, *David* didn't want to kill אבנר *Abner*. All that
happened in between and then that's why I was reading all that
yesterday.
But somewhere there, and I don't remember where it was, it talked
about דוד David, *David*'s children and it mentions שלמה *Shlomo* even before
this. So like, so we're going to, we're sort of going to
get to that. So but just keep that, just keep that in
mind.
I wish I remember where the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* was when I
was reading it. Okay, anyway,
so let's continue.
Says, so we're just reading the פסוקים *pesukim* had he had these
six, and then later on, מכדאמר ליה נביא Navi אם מעט ואוסיפה
לך כהנה וכהנה *mikidamreilei navi im meat ve'osifah lach kaheina ve'kaheina*. So,
and if that's too little for you, you would have gotten more
here, more there, like this and like this. So כהנה שש *kaheina
sheis*, you had six, so I'm going to give you another כהנה
*kaheina*, which is so that's another six, וכהנה שש *ve'kaheina sheis*, so
you know, כהנה כהנה *kaheina kaheina* is so six, six, and six.
So the most he can have is 18.
Okay, so דהוו ליה תריסר *de'havei leih tlamisar*, כמאן דאמר רבינא
אם כהנה תרתי *k'man de'amar Ravina im kaheina tartei*. No, so okay,
so if you have כהנה כהנה *kaheina kaheina*, right, so you get,
so you get the six you had, another כהנה *kaheina* is six,
and then כהנה *kaheina* is so it's cumulative, right, is 12, right?
So you have six and six is 12, and then another כהנה
*kaheina* כנגד *k'neged* all that is, so you have 12 and 12
is 24. So עשרים וארבע *esrim ve'arba*. תניא נמי הכי לא ירבה
לו נשים ויותר
מעשרים וארבע
*Tanya nami hachi lo yarbeh lo nashim v'yoser m'esrim ve'arba*. So conveniently
we're going to find teachings to support every contention we're going to
have here. So the first one is 18, right? So maybe, or
maybe it's 24. Yes, that's right. There's another source that says 24.
And למאן דאמר
שש *ul'man de'amar sheis* and you say כהנה *kaheina* is six, so
six and six is 12, ו- *ve-* so another 12 and then
כהנה *kaheina* which is כנגד *k'neged* all that, which is another 24.
So 6, 6, 12, 24, so you're going to get 48. ארבעים
ושמונה הוו *arba'im u'shemoneh hava*. תניא נמי הכי לא ירבה לו נשים
ויותר מארבעים ושמונה *Tanya nami hachi lo yarbeh lo nashim v'yoser me'arba'im
u'shemoneh*. Guess what, we have a teaching you can't have, you can't
have more than 48. All right, so you can have quite a
lot of wives.
תנא דידן מאי טעמא אמר רב כהנה מקיש כהנה בתרא לכהנה קמא
מה כהנה
קמא שש אף כהנה בתרא
שש *Tana didan mai ta'ama amar rav kahana makish kaheina basra l'kaheina
kamma mah
kaheina kamma sheis af kaheina basra sheis*.
Okay, anyway, it's like we're saying before, to get back to the
12 thing, just so the כהנה *kaheina* and the כהנה *kaheina* if
you say that it's 18, so you have six and then you
have כהנה *kaheina* another six and then the last כהנה *kaheina* is
the same thing, another six. So that's why we have 18, but
wait, we were just
quoting the six wives and if you notice, none of them were
מיכל Michal *Michal* or מירב *Meirav*, but they're all different people.
והא הויא מיכל Michal *ve'ha havya Michal* tari saying it's six, he
had
another wife,
but again, the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that we had were the children
he had and he may or may not have had children from
מיכל Michal *Michal*, like that was that whole מחלוקת machloket. *machlokes* we
had before.
But anyway, but he at least had her as a wife. But
then again, if that was sort of like a מחלוקת machloket. *machlokes*,
but the תורה Torah *Torah* is, the נביא *Navi* is very explicit
that he was married to מיכל Michal, *Michal*. So אמר רב עגלה
Egla זו מיכל Michal? *amar rav egla zu michal*. One of the
women mentioned was עגלה *Egla*, which is a very weird name for
a woman. So we're saying really that's מיכל Michal *Michal* and עגלה
*Egla*'s just like a term of affection. ולמה נקרא שמה עגלה שחביבה
עליו כעגלה *velamah nikra shemah egla she'havivah alav k'egla*. You know, she
was beloved to him like an עגלה *egla*, וכן הוא אומר *v'chein
hu omer* with שמשון *Shimshon*, לולי חרשתם בעגלתי לא מצאתם חידתי *lulei
charashtem b'eglati lo
metzasem chidosi*. Had you not
sort of plowed with my עגלה *egla*, meaning had you not extracted
it from my wife, you would not have found out the answer
to the riddle which he had asked them, which is not relevant
to this גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* right now. So okay, but wait a
minute. So now we're saying he married מיכל *Michal* and מיכל *Michal*
is עגלה *Egla* and then he had children from this marriage. ומי
הוו למיכל בנים *u'mi ha'avu l'michal banim*? Did מיכל *Michal* really have
children? והכתיב Vehaketiv... ולמיכל בת שאול Shaul לא היה לה ילד עד
יום מותה *ve'hakesiv u'lmichal bas shaul lo hayah lah yalad ad yom
mosah*. So she did not have a child until יום *yom*, until
the day she died. Interesting, if you look at some of the
ways it was quoted, some of it will say ילד *yeled*. So
was it a י
*yud* or a ו *vav*? Anyway. she didn't have a kid until
the day she died and this was because she saw דוד David
dancing around, you know, with the ארון aron and she says like,
מה נכבד היום מלך ישראל, mah nichbad hayom melech Yisrael, you know,
he's dancing with everyone כהגלות נגלות אחד
הריקים,
kehiglot niglot achad hareikim,
like, you
know, like one of the commoners, you know, these empty people, you
know, what are you doing demeaning yourself? You know, he says like,
what do you mean? I'm not demeaning
myself by dancing, you
know, and I'll be doing even more of that and even with
these שפחות, shfachot, you know, I'll be dancing and you know, I'll
be viewed with esteem amongst them. So anyway, then it says after
that מיכל בת שאול, Michal bat Shaul, she didn't have offspring until
the day she died. So how are we saying that she had
kids? The נביא says she didn't. אמר חסדא עד יום מותה לא
היה לה ביום מותה היה לה. Amar Chisda ad yom motah lo
hayah lah beyom motah hayah lah. Okay, so the day she died
she had kids, meaning maybe she died in childbirth, right? So yes,
יתרעם, Yitream יתרעם Yitream or you know... so she had יתרעם Yitream,
the day she died. So or another answer, מפני בניה שחשבו הוא
בחברון. mipne baneha shechashavu hu beHebron.
But wait, the children that were mentioned here are children from you
know, that he had in חברון. Hebron. ואילו מעשה דמיכל בירושלים הוה.
Ve'ilu ma'aseh deMichal beYerushalayim havah.
But the whole thing with מיכל was in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, that's where
they were bringing the ארון aron to, to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. דכתיב ומיכל
בת שאול נשקפה בעד החלון ותרא את המלך דוד מפזז ומכרכר לפני
ה' ותבז Dechtiv u'Michal bat Shaul nishkafa be'ad hachalon vatere et hamelech
David mefazeiz u'mecharkeir lifnei Hashem vativez and so on and so forth.
Anyway, you know, we didn't quote the part that says ירושלים, Yerushalayim.
but obviously all that was ירושלים, Yerushalayim, they were bringing the ארון
aron back to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So
how
did she have children in חברון, Hebron, right? ואמר רב יהודה ואיתימא
רב יוסף שכלתה מיכל דמטרפה. Ve'amar Rav Yehuda ve'itayma Rav Yosef shekaltah
Michal demitrefah.
So she got what she deserved by, you know, by saying this
to the king. So fine, how do we explain all this? לא
אימא עד אותו מעשה היה לה מכאן ואילך לא היה לה. Lo
ema ad oto ma'aseh hayah lah mikan ve'eilach lo hayah lah. So
which is nice in some ways, it you know, it retreats from
a bite of this, right, that she didn't have any children. Okay,
so from then on she didn't have any children, but she had
children before. Because remember דוד was first king in חברון, Hebron, then
after this whole thing with the שאול camp and then you know,
finally he won everyone over to his side, then he was king
over everybody and went to ירושלים. Yerushalayim So, you know, that's what
the פסוק pasuk is saying. While he's in חברון, Hebron, having like
a somewhat smaller kingdom, he had all these children. And so he
had children from מיכל in חברון, Hebron, then this whole thing happened
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and then she had no more children. So she
did at least get to have some children.
So that's how we're answering it to
so we can still maintain that מיכל is עגלה and that he
had children, and the פסוק pasuk, that says that she didn't have
children was from a later point.
Okay, so now you have to remember also that what we were
saying is that, you know, what you could have said is
if you remember we said that when we had חמישה בני מיכל,
chamesha bnei Michal, right? So you know, the פסוק pasuk over here
says you know one, this guy whatever his name was, I'm forgetting,
יתרעם, Yitream, right? But then we also had that פסוק, pasuk this
is what we were quoting on י"ט ע"ב, yud tet amud bet,
we had a פסוק that says that she had חמישה בני מיכל
בת שאול. chamesha bnei Michal bat Shaul. What about that? So maybe
she had more, you know, after that in חברון. Hebron.
But the way we explain it was מרב ילדה מיכל גידלה בכך
נקראו על שמה. Merav yaldah Michal giddelah bekach nikreu al shemah. So
you still could have said that she really didn't have any children,
right? But מיכל, you know, raised these children, so therefore they're called
hers. But it says ילדה, yaldah, which means you know, she gave
birth to them. But anyway, we could have potentially answered it that
way and not in the, you know, not go over here, but
oh maybe she had children, whatever. The גמרא Gemara was willing to
say that, you know, even if you don't have children they may
be considered yours. So that's a potential other answer.
Did we say that earlier, was that what you were just saying?
That's what I was just saying.
Yeah, yeah, that's what you were saying.
So right, so maybe she raised this יתרעם, maybe that was one
of them, I don't know, you know. So she may not have
given birth.
Okay,
so she didn't have any children after. והכתיב... Okay,
anyway, fine. Now we're saying דוד you know would have to content
himself with eighteen or you know, maybe forty-eight depending on how many
you get up to. והכתיב ויקח דוד עוד פלגשים ונשים מירושלים. Vehaketiv
vayikach David od pilagshim venashim miYerushalayim. He took more, he took more
you know פלגשים pilagshim and he had more wives in ירושלים. Yerushalayim,
So he didn't have
eighteen? משמונה עשרה, mishmoneh esrei, yeah, that's to get you to the
eighteen. He had six and then he went to ירושלים Yerushalayim? and
he had more,
and that's what he did. So that's not a problem.
שמונה ב' ה', shmoneh bet hey, maybe that's what it was, שמונה
ב' ה'. shmoneh bet hey.
Where is it?
Oh yeah, here it is. ואלה, Veeleh, that's what I wanted to
do. ויקח דוד עוד פלגשים ונשים בירושלים אחרי באו מחברון ויולדו עוד
לדוד בנים ובנות, Vayikach David od pilagshim venashim bi-rushalayim acharei bo'o mi-Chevron
vayivaldu od le-David banim u-vanot, you know sons and daughters. אלה שמות
הילודים לו בירושלים: Eileh shemot hayiludim lo bi-rushalayim: שמוע, Shammua, and שובב,
Shobab, and נתן, Nathan, and שלמה,
right?
שלמה is one of them. ויבחר, Ve-Yivchar, ואלישוע, ve-Elishua, ונפג, ve-Nefeg, ויפיע,
ve-Yafia, ואלישמע, ve-Elishama, ואלידע, ve-Eliada, ואליפלט. ve-Elifalet.
So all these people
and then you have the whole thing with בת שבע, right? And
then and then later on שלמה was born. So
but שלמה was born here, so that's what I'm saying, this may
be sort of like a like a prelude, like a presage. You
know, like sometimes when you you know like a
like an author will like sort of give things away then develop
the plot later, so that might be that. So like I just
wanted to point that out. So like you know so you may
still say that you can get to the eighteen and you know
we had all, we had all these things and we're just talking
about all his in totality, all the children he had in ירושלים,
Yerushalayim but not right now, not at this point.
So that kind of helps. All right.
He had children in ירושלים, Yerushalayim. but I thought we were talking
about the ones who were
born to him in חברון. Chevron. Yeah we were, but like you
know but but this says now we're just having that question, right?
So like you know if we're saying that he had eighteen in
all, how do we say that he had all these you know
wives in ירושלים? Sounds like he had a lot of wives and
you know more than eighteen. I'll get you to eighteen, that was
the you know, but yes, we had חברון, Chevron, but then he
had children in ירושלים and you know and part of that, the
reason why we were trying to do that is like what happened
to מיכל? Then we're saying that מיכל was one of these,
who he did marry her first before he was king in ירושלים.
So okay.
מאי נשים מאי פלגשים? Mai nashim mai pilagshim? Now what's the difference
between a wife and a and a פילגש? pilegesh? אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב: Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav: נשים בכתובה
ובקידושין, nashim be-ketubah u-ve-kiddushin, you know wife is like what you'd think,
you know you have, you do קידושין, kiddushin, she has a כתובה.
ketubah. פלגשים בלא כתובה ובלא קידושין, pilagshim belo ketubah u-velo kiddushin, neither.
It means, it's sort of like a sexual relationship basically. Just,
just a sexual relationship. I mean, you know, there may be some
level of support while you know you're with her maybe, I'm not
getting there, but she definitely doesn't get anything once you know you
die.
So is that allowed? Yeah. Because
you could have a sexual
relationship apparently.
Like yeah, I mean, which is obviously we're not so happy about
that, you know like is that allowed for everybody? You know like
under what circumstances? We're not at all getting into that. But you
know but at least put it this way, at least biblically you
had, you had a lot of that, right? ופילגשו ושמה ראומה ותלד
גם היא, U-filagsho u-shema Re'umah va-teled gam hi,
you know
like we have all these, like you know אברהם Avraham had פילגשים.
pilagshim.
ובני הפילגשים אשר לאברהם, U-vnei ha-pilagshim asher le-Avraham,
you know like yeah, and then, right, so some people and you
hear this every so often, you know, in the religious community it
comes up that
like can you take a פילגש pilegesh or not? Like you know,
that's really viewed unfavorably. Is it like technically legal? You know like
that's not, you know that's like I'm not going to go there,
I don't know, I didn't research it, because it's really just a
line in passing in the גמרא. Gemara
But you know was
again like is that supposed to be normative practice or was that
like you know biblical practice, that just for a king, is that
just for the very wealthy? You know what I mean? You know,
those are all potential questions which I did not research.
Can you marry the concubine afterwards?
I don't see why not. I mean like you can always do
קידושין kiddushin with somebody, right? Right. But you know
can she, then if there's no כתובה ketubah and there's no, can
she sleep with somebody else? You know what I mean? Like that's
another question. Can she?
Right, yeah. You know, interesting, yes.
Right? So it's like
very specific here that there's no כתובה ketubah and קידושין. kiddushin. דאמר
רב יהודה אמר רב ארבע מאות
ילדים נולדו לדוד
וכולם
בני יפת תואר היו מגדלי בלוריות היו.
De-amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav arba me'ot yeladim
noldu le-David
ve-khullam bnei
yefat to'ar hayu megadlei beloriot hayu. So and we're going
to, this is going to come up you know a lot more
later. So you had 400 children, all of them were בני יפת
תואר. bnei yefat to'ar. So יפת תואר yefat to'ar is like you
know that's כי תצא Ki Tetzei when you see the beautiful captive,
not beautiful but you know she might be beautiful or you just
you know want to be with this woman. So then you know
then you take her, you know there's this whole ritual that's mentioned
in the תורה Torah that you do.
Were these his children?
So yeah, let me let me get to this. So anyway, so
then there's, so that's what יפת תואר yefat to'ar is. So דוד
was a very martial king. You know, there was a lot of
wars. So he went to war a lot. So you know, so
he desired these women. So apparently he had relations with them and
had all these kids. So he had 400 kids from יפת תואר.
yefat to'ar. So that means you know 400 times.
And they all had these בלוריות. beloriot. So now this is a
very big problem. The בלורית belorit is sort of like this braid
that, you know, they had on the back but like it was
a very like דרכי האמורי darkhei ha-Emori thing, might have even been
an עבודה זרה avodah zarah thing, right? It's totally חוקות הגויים. chukkot
ha-goyim. At least on the surface, but let me get to that.
בכולן יושבין בקרונות של זהב ומהלכין בראשי גייסות היו והן בעלי אגרופים
של בית דוד. bechulan yoshvin bekronot shel zahav umalchin beroshei geisyot hayu
vehen ba'alei egrofim shel beit David. So, so these used to sit
in these בקרונות של זהב, bekronot shel zahav, these golden chariots and,
you know, they're at the head of the troops and, you know,
they were like these, like strong, big strong kind of, you know,
men over there. So, so,
this is a very big problem as I was saying
because like, you know, this is like a total like דרכי אמורי
Darchei Emori thing. How are they, how are you allowed to do
that? And there's a couple of problems, you know, which I'll mention.
So one is,
how can they have these בלוריות? bloryot? So, there is a,
here, let me get the רמב״ם, Rambam, הלכות עבודה זרה, Hilchot Avodah
Zarah, פרק יא, Perek Yud Aleph, הלכה א. Halacha Aleph. Not a
lot,
a lot of things you can't do.
You know, אין הולכים בחוקות הגויים, ein holchin bechukot hagoyim, לא מדמים
להם, lo medamim lahem, you can't, you know, you can't be like
them. לא במלבוש ולא בשער, lo bemalbush velo bese'ar, not with their
clothes, not with their hair, וכיוצא בהן, vechayotzei bahen, and things like
that. שנאמר ובחוקות הגוי—and shene'emar uvechukot hagoy ובחוקותיהם לא תלכו. uvechukoteihem lo
telechu. He gives all these—שנאמר השמר לך פן תנקש אחריהם. shene'emar hishamer
lecha pen tinakesh achareihem. All these לאווין. lavin. The תורה Torah warns
you from being like them.
So, לא ילבש מלבוש המיוחד להם ולא יגדל ציצית כמו ציצית ראשם,
lo yilbash malbush hamiyuchad lahem velo yigadel tzitzit kemo tzitzit rosham, which
is this, you know, you can't have your hair like that, this
בלורית. blorit. He
says ולא יגלח מן הצדדים, velo yegalach min hatzdadim, can't like shave
your hair on the sides, ויניח השער באמצע, veyaniach hase'ar be'emtza, and
have the hair in the middle,
כמו שהם עושים, kemo shehem osim, וזהו הנקרא בלורית. vezehu hanikra blorit.
This specific לאו, lav, you know, according to the רמב״ם, Rambam, you
really can't do that.
So what is the היתר? heter? So now, you know, he says
ישראל שהיה קרוב למלכות וצריך לישב לפני מלכיהם ויהיה גנאי אם לא
ידמה להן. Yisrael shehayah karov lamalchut vetzarich liyeshev lifnei malcheihem veyehei gnai
im lo yidameh lahen. If you are in a position, you, a
Jew, in a position where you need to be amongst non-Jewish royalty,
this is among Jewish royalty with דוד, but anyways, you need to
be among non-Jewish royalty, הרי זה מותר ללבוש כמלבושן ולגלח השער כנגד
פניו כדרך שהם עושים. harei zeh mutar lilbosh kemalbushan ulegalach hase'ar keneged
panav kederech shehem osim. So there is some latitude to, you know,
be a little bit more like them.
So now what he, and then, so the כסף משנה Kesef Mishneh
quotes that בפרק עגלה ערופה, bePerek Eglah Arufah, אבטולוס בר ראובן
התירו לו לספר קומי מפני שהוא קרוב למלכות.
Avtulos bar Reuven hitiro
lo lesaper kumi mipnei shehu karov lamalchut. He, you know, he got
like this special non-Jewish haircut because he was amongst, you know,
non-Jewish royalty. And then, וזהו ממה שהתירו מלבושים וכל שכן הוא. vezehu
mimah shehitiro malbushim vechol sheken hu. So,
so the רמב״ם Rambam learns from here the, you know, not just
the hair, but also the clothes. Then he goes on that,
so he says wait, ואם תאמר כיון שכתב רבינו שלוקה על כל
אחד מאלו, ve'im tomar keivan shekatav Rabbeinu shelokei al kol echad me'elu,
this, like this is a לאו, lav, if you, if you do
these kind of things, you get מלקות. malkut. So,
היאך היה כח ביד חכמים להתיר איסור תורה לקרובי מלכות? heich hayah
koach beyad chachamim lehatir issur Torah likrovei malchut? How could, you know,
the רמב״ם Rambam say oh, it's okay if you're קרובי למלכות, krovei
lamalchut, you can sort of do things like
the non-Jews. ויש לומר שמשום הצלת ישראל הוא דשרו. veyesh lomar shemishum
hatzalat Yisrael hu desharu.
So okay, if you're קרובי למלכות krovei lamalchut and you're in a
position to like really, you know, affect policy, which could be for
the betterment of the Jewish people, maybe even saving their lives, then
דשרו, desharu, then that's allowed, like sort of like פיקוח נפש, pikuach
nefesh, right? Allows you all these sorts of things. Where do you
get that from? What? I'm meaning from that, from the כסף משנה,
Kesef Mishneh, the commenting on the רמב״ם. Rambam. Right, right. In הלכות
עבודה זרה, Hilchot Avodah Zarah, יא, Yud Aleph, הלכה ג. Halacha Gimel.
But I read also הלכה א. Halacha Aleph. Right. ויש לומר שמשום
הצלת ישראל הוא דשרו דשלוחי ומלמדי סניא מלכים הם ומצילים את
בני ישראל.
veyesh lomar shemishum
hatzalat Yisrael hu desharu deshluchi umelamdei sanyei melachim hem umatzilim et benei
Yisrael. And then he mentions this, the four hundred ילדים yeladim that
were with דוד, נמי הצלת ישראל הוא דהוו
מבעתים את האויבים. nami hatzalat Yisrael hu dehavu meva'atim et ha'oyvim. So,
so this is how it was allowed because they put them in
the front. There were these big, you know, strong men and you
know, and then it looked completely non-Jewish. So if the non-Jewish enemies
would see these like very non-Jewish looking people in the front, oh
my god, even, even, you know, he has support among the broad
populace, what chance do we have, right? So, so that's the היתר,
heter, according to כסף משנה Kesef Mishneh for this. How they were
allowed to have this בלורית, blorit, which is very, very forbidden.
אי נמי שהתורה לא פרטה דבר אלא אמרה ובחוקותיהם לא תלכו. ee
nami shehaTorah lo partah davar ela amrah uvechukoteihem lo telechu. Torah didn't
say what way, right? The רמב״ם Rambam is saying okay, it means
you can't dress like them, you can't have their haircut like them.
All it says is don't go based on their customs, right? ומסרו
הדבר לחכמים והם ראו שאין לגזור על קרובי למלכות. umasru hadavar lachachamim
vehem ra'u she'ein ligzor al krovei lamalchut. So the, the Torah said
okay, you know, the Torah made it very nebulous and the חכמים
chachamim have latitude to explain which
cases
it applies and which it doesn't. So it didn't apply in this
case.
And that's what חייא Chiyya says too, you know.
Probably the same thing.
Yeah. About all of this. רמב״ם Rambam and כסף משנה. Kesef Mishneh.
Okay, but there's another problem.
He said that, that the children originally might not have been Jewish
and then they might have converted them. Yeah.
But, I mean this is a better, I think this is, yeah,
this is a better explanation. But you know, so, but there's another
problem, right? There's the and so the problem is that
and
that then it discusses it is that so there's a question about
what you're allowed to do with the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. So
there's a question about what you're allowed to do with the אשת
יפת תואר. eshet yifat to'ar. Right? It says, כי חשקת בה ולקחת
לך לאישה, ki chashakta bah velakachta lecha le-ishah, so you want her,
you take her as a woman, והבאתה אל תוך ביתך וגילחה את
ראשה ועשתה את ציפורניה,
ve-havetah el toch beitecha ve-gilchah et
roshah ve-aseta et tziporneha, והסירה את שמלת שביה מעליה, ve-hesirah et simlat
shivyah me-aleha, and then the question is when can you be with
her, and if you are with her, what happens next? So the
גמרא in קידושין Kiddushin asks: can you have relations with her immediately,
even while she's still a גויה, goya, even before she goes through
this whole process or not? And the גמרא says there's a מחלוקת.
machloket. רב says that ביאה ראשונה, bi'ah rishonah, the first relation, you
can have right away. Right? It says, כי חשקת בה ולקחת לך
לאישה, ki chashakta bah velakachta lecha le-ishah, so you want her, you
take her as a woman, והבאתה אל תוך ביתך וגילחה את ראשה
ועשתה את ציפורניה, ve-havetah el toch beitecha ve-gilchah et roshah ve-aseta et
tziporneha, והסירה את שמלת שביה מעליה, ve-hesirah et simlat shivyah me-aleha, ואחר
כן, ve-achar ken, so after he does all this, תבוא אליה ובעלתה,
tavo eleiha u-ve’altah, you can have sex with her, right? והיתה לך
לאישה, ve-hayeta lecha le-ishah, then she can be your wife. So it
seems like that she has to go through all this and then
you can have children with her. Except for the, but that’s the
מחלוקת. Now, the תורה Torah doesn't say that. So that's the question.
But in the heat of battle they say, that's the question.
So the question is, in the heat of battle, so there’s two
ways of explaining it. One is you can have sex with her
once, then if you want to continue the relationship she has to
go through all this, right? Or you can say the תורה Torah
says alright, I know, the תורה Torah gave you this out once
because they know you're not going to listen otherwise, but if you
want to continue it then you know you got to do something.
Others say no, like you know the תורה Torah is completely referring
to the יצר הרע, yetzer hara, you're going to want this, so
the תורה Torah says alright, I'll let you do it, even the
first time, only after this whole ritual. So that's the מחלוקת. And
so according to those let's say, you can't even have sex with
her until you do all this, then they're already Jewish. So once
they're Jewish, how can דוד have let
that happen?
Right? So
then that could be the answer of קרובה למלכות, kerovah le-malchut, then
they get a special dispensation. Yeah.
And
so
and I'm going to get back to that, I hope, because I'm
going to, this is the next thing, I'm not done with this
concept, so just bear that in the back of your mind. So
anyway these 400 kids were daughters of יפת תואר. yifat to'ar. ואמר
יהודה אמר רב תמר בת יפת תואר היתה. ve-amar yehuda amar rav
tamar bat yifat to'ar hayeta.
So תמר, Tamar, remember there's אמנון Amnon and תמר, Tamar, אמנון Amnon
desired his half-sister, they're from different mothers, אמנון Amnon
desired his half-sister תמר Tamar and then you know what to do,
so אמנון Amnon. had a friend that suggested this whole thing, pretend
to be sick and then say oh only way I can get
better is תמר Tamar comes and makes something in front of me
and I'm going to eat it and then that's what happened, then
he let everyone go, he chased everyone out of the room, so
תמר, Tamar, that's it, go sleep with me. She said what do
you mean? How can I possibly do this? And he raped her.
Right? Then אבשלום kills אמנון. So that was that whole thing. So
now we're going to talk about that. ואמר יהודה אמר רב תמר
בת יפת תואר היתה שנאמר ועתה דבר נא אל המלך כי לא
ימנעני ממך. ve-amar yehuda amar rav tamar bat yifat to'ar hayeta she-ne'emar
ve-atah daber na el ha-melech ki lo yimna'eni mimcha. So תמר Tamar
says no look, listen, don't do this, speak to the king because
he's not, he'll let me be with you. What do you mean?
How can you say that? This is you know even though they
were half-sisters but they're half-brother and sister, but it's from the same
father, you still can't marry her. So how could he possibly say
that the king will let you know, will not withhold me from
you? How could she possibly have said that? So it must be
that she's a יפת תואר. yifat to'ar. מכדי בת אחוה מניסוין הויא
אחוה היא ואי שרי ליה? michdi bat achva me-nisuin hava achva hi
ve-i sharei lei? She was his sister. אלא שמע מינה בת יפת
תואר היתה. ela shema mina bat yifat to'ar hayeta. So she was
a בת יפת תואר. bat yifat to'ar. And okay and then that
though raises the question. We understand that you know that we say
that it was a one-time thing, you're allowed to have sex with
the יפת תואר yifat to'ar once. That's where this you know that's
how it could have happened. But if you're not allowed to have
sex with her once even until you go through the whole ritual,
then by the time the whole ritual is done she's Jewish, right?
Then so how does that solve the problem? So that's תוספות's Tosafot
question.
So and by the way so since we should be doing ירושלמי,
Yerushalmi, this we look in the middle of תוספות, Tosafot, מחלוקת בירושלמי
בין רב ושמואל, רב אמר אינה מותרת במלחמה אלא ביאה ראשונה, ושמואל
אמר אף לא ביאה ראשונה. machloket bi-yerushalmi bein rav u-shmuel, rav amar
eina muteret ba-milchamah ela bi-ah rishonah, ve-shmuel amar af lo bi-ah rishonah.
So רב says you can do it once, that's what you were
saying, but שמואל Shmuel says not even once. So then how קשיא
לדוכתה? kashya le-duktah? So then we have the same question, how is
this
allowed, right? How could תמר Tamar have said it if her mother
was already Jewish? She may have been taken as captive as a
יפת תואר, yifat to'ar, but by the time she was born she
must have been Jewish because the mother was already Jewish at that
point before you know you can only live with her once she's
Jewish according to that opinion.
And I think we discussed long ago that if you conceive before
the woman converted then הלכתית halachically she's not, correct,
correct, so but the question is if according to that opinion you're
not allowed to have sex with her until she's
Jewish. Right. No, okay, right. So that's the first opinion. The first
opinion says yeah, the first time, right? So first time it's allowed,
so then you know she could have even given birth before she
was converted. You don't know how long this conversion process takes, you
know.
So
you know or she was conceived already then converted some month later,
whatever, so you could have said that. But according to the opinion
that says you can't even be with her once until she's converted,
then how do you answer that? So I'm going to skip a
little. אם כן im ken תוספות Tosafot says קשיא לשמואל טובא טובא
kashya le-shmuel tuva tuva כדפריש אלא הכי נראה לי לומר דתמר לא
היתה בת דוד שאמה כבר היתה עוברת כשבאה למלחמה. kedefarish ela hachi
nireh li lomar de-tamar lo hayeta bat david she-imah kvar hayeta uberet
kesheb-ah la-milchamah.
She wasn't, she was a יפת תואר, yifat to'ar, maybe even you
can't have relations with her once, but maybe this woman was already
pregnant with תמר Tamar from whoever it was she was with, her
non-Jewish boyfriend, right? So תמר's Tamar mother... was not Jewish, taken as
יפת תואר, yefat toar, she was already pregnant with Tamar, then David,
you know, did this whole ritual, married her and then had sex
with her. So even according to the opinion that says you can't
even have the first contact until after she's Jewish, her mother already
was pregnant with her beforehand. Answer one.
Or you could just say, you know, like,
sort of. Look in תוספות Tosafos בד"ה b'd'h מתוך שגדלה בחיקו של
דוד קראו לה בת המלך, mitoch shegadla b'cheiko shel David karu lah
bat hamelech, right?
So you can say, so why she's considered David's daughter, if she
was already, you know, her mother was already pregnant with her from
somebody else? Okay, she grew up in the king's house, so she's
called David's daughter. Or you can say the same idea that like,
you know, she's considered David's daughter, she could have even had this
kid
already, but then she grew up in David's house, right? So those
are all ways of getting out of it. So you can even
say that this can't prove necessarily one way or the other about
if you're allowed to have that initial contact with the יפת תואר
yefat toar or not. Anyway, so I wanted to get to that.
Get to the bottom of the page at least.
So getting back to this whole Tamar thing, ואמנון רע ושמו יונדב
בן שמעה אחי דוד. v'Amnon rai v'shmo Yonadav ben Shima achi David.
So his nephew. So this guy, איש חכם, ish chacham, was you
know, and he advised on how to get about to be with
Tamar. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב איש חכם היה לרשעה, Amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav ish chacham haya l'risha, yeah, he was smart but
like, you know, in a wicked way because he suggested this whole
ruse. ויאמר לו מדוע אתה ככה דל בן המלך ויאמר לו יונדב
שכב על מטתך והתחלה
vayoimer lo madua ata kacha dal ben hamelech vayoimer lo Yonadav shachav
al
mitatcha v'hitchala and עד שיבאו בני הבריות ad sheyavo'u b'nei habriyot and
וכחמי מן שתעשה לפניך. v'chami min sheta'aseh lefanecha. So
it goes through the whole thing, like I mentioned. So,
you know, okay, you know, go make this whole thing and, you
know, the only way to get better is to say Tamar needs
to make me this stuff. And then she did and she took
the pan, you know, like poured the oil, made the batter and,
you know, made these like these things. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב
שעשתה לו מיני טיגון. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav she'asta lo minei
tigun. So she made something that's fried because otherwise he could have
asked, why she need to do it in front of him, right?
Like, you know, why her, right? Let them bring whatever, let them
cook something in the kitchen, you know, and bring it over. Why
she have to do it in front of him? So the answer
is no, wants you know, nice hot and fried. You know, so
something like fried sort of loses its crispness if it takes too
long. So it needs to be like nice and fresh. So he
wants fresh food. Then after that he raped her. וישנא אמנון שנאה
גדולה מאד. vayisna Amnon sina gedola meod. So then he hated her,
right? He really like, you know, even more than, you know, and
that's what happens. Sometimes you know, strong passion can go, you know,
from one way to the other. And he probably hated himself, you
know, then you know, looking at her reminded him always of his
transgression. מאי תמר ויתקע נימא בקשור ושוויה ככרות שפכה. mai Tamar v'yitka
nima b'kishur v'shavya k'chrut shofcha.
So she had, you know, she had pubic hair and that like,
you know, sort of like emasculated him. Very, very weird. וכי נימא
בקשור ליה מאי עבדא, v'chi nima b'kishur lei mai avda,
how's that her fault? Right? No, the answer is אלא אימא קשרה
לו נימא ועשתה לו כרות שפכה. ela eima kashra lo nima v'asta
lo k'rut shofcha. That's interesting. So she sort of like, you know,
she sort of gets back at him. He's raping her, but then
he emasculates, then she emasculates him.
I'm not sure if she emasculates him or maybe, you know,
you mentioned a member,
but I don't know, I'm just reading the English. But I mean
כרת karet maybe that it is making him what do you call
it,
sterile? No, not sterile, but just that it means that he can't
do certain things because he's not whole. I mean that would be
a כהן. kohen.
I think it means that he actually כרת karet ויהיה לו כרות
שפכה בקהל ה', v'yiyeh lo k'rut shofcha b'kehal Hashem,
you know, that he can't give, he can't have children anymore. So
it's, makes him sterile somehow. So she sort of like, you know,
resists him, you know, at least. Right. איני והא דאמר רבא
מאי דכתיב ויצא שמך
בגוים ביופיך, eini v'ha d'amar Rava
mai d'chtiv vayeitzei shemech
bagoyim b'yofyeich,
you know, your name will go out amongst all the other nations.
And we learn from that שאין להם לבנות ישראל לא סרחת השחי
ולא בית הערוה. she'ein lahem livnot Yisrael lo sarchat hashachi v'lo beit
ha'erva. They do not have hair in the underarms, you know, or
in the nether regions. So how can we say that, you know,
that he became a כרות שפכה k'rut shofcha either because of this
or. So what does that mean? That's very bizarre. They don't have
hair? I mean, of course women have hair. So, you know, so
people go through these through these contortions to like try to figure
this out. The easy answer is that they, you know, at society
at large, they didn't shave, but the Jewish women shaved, you know?
So that's what it is. It's not they don't grow hair. Of
course they grow hair. Like do we say that people, you know,
now women have hair? And like so what happened, נשתנה הטבע, nishtana
hateva, you know, you don't have to go there. You can just
say that like, you know, they were very מקפיד makpid to shave,
you know, nice smooth, nice and smooth. I mean women shave now
too. Not not always, not everywhere. But, you know, at that time
it might have been the custom among Jewish women, they just shaved.
That's what you can just say. So how could Tamar have done
that? ושאני תמר דבת יפת תואר הוי. v'shani Tamar d'bat yefat toar
havi. We just said that. She was a, she was a בת
יפת תואר. bat yefat toar. Or you can just say a better
answer would be
that
she
is. But the single woman she wasn't going to be having sex
for instance so she didn't need to shave. So ותקח תמר
אפר על ראשה וכתונת הפסים אשר עליה קרעה, Vatikach Tamar efer al
roshah u’ketonet hapasim asher aleha kara'ah, so she was in אבילות, aveilut,
she rent her garments, she put ash on herself. תני בשם רבי
יהושע בן
קרחה גדר גדול גדרה תמר באותה שעה, Tani b’shem Rabi Yehoshua ben
Korcha gader gadol gadrah Tamar b’otah sha'ah, because of this they made
a very big fence so to speak and we're going to explain
what that means. אמרו בנות מלכים כך בנות הדיוטות על אחת כמה
וכמה אם לצנועות כך לפרוצות על אחת כמה וכמה. Amru bnot melachim
kach bnot hedyotot al achat kama v’chama im l’tznuot kach l’frutzot al
achat kama v’chama. If this can happen to the daughter of a
king who was very modest, קל וחומר kal v’chomer to anyone else.
So אמר יהודה באותה שעה גזרו על הייחוד
ועל הפנויה. Amar Yehuda b’otah sha’ah gazru al ha’yichud v’al ha’p’nuya. So
you can't be in seclusion and they also had you can't and
also פנויה, p’nuya, a single woman. What do we mean by this?
ייחוד דאורייתא הוא. Yichud d’Oraita hu. Being with a married woman, you
can't be with a married woman alone. That's a תורה Torah. thing,
that's the whole point, that's how סוטה Sotah starts, right? So anyway,
דאמר יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק
רמז לייחוד מן
התורה
מנין.
d’amar Yochanan
mishum Rabi Shimon ben Yehotzadak remez l’yichud min haTorah minalan.
A רמז, remez, where's, it's a פסוק according to this, שנאמר כי
יסיתך אחיך
בן אמך
shenemar ki yesit’cha achicha
ben imecha that
when the,
this is to worship עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So if your brother,
the son of your mother, right,
he's your brother of course,
presumably the son of your mother or could obviously be from father.
But anyway the point is וכי בן אם מסית בן אב אינו
מסית? v’chi ben em mesit ben av eino mesit? Why is it
saying if the brother, the son of your mother? Is it only
the son of your mother that can
potentially influence you to do עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? But the son
of your father won't? It doesn't make a difference who it is,
right? Just say your brother. וכי בן אם מסית בן אב אינו
מסית? v’chi ben em mesit ben av eino mesit?
So no, אלא לומר לך בן מתייחד עם אמו ואין אחר מתייחד
עם כל עריות
שבתורה. ela lomar lach ben mityached im imo v’ein acher mityached im
kol arayot shebaTorah.
So it means no, just like a son can be with his
mother, it's not a problem of ייחוד, yichud, but anyone else it
would be a problem of ייחוד. yichud. That's how we know ייחוד
yichud is from the תורה. So anyway what do you need at
that time they גזרו gazru on ייחוד? yichud? That already was something
that you couldn't do. אלא אימא גזרו על ייחוד דפנויה. ela eima
gazru al yichud d’p’nuya.
So no, what it means is not על ייחוד ועל פנויה, al
yichud v’al p’nuya, not two separate things, but rather until then, unmarried
men and women could be together alone because it's not עריות arayot
to each other, it's not a problem, it's not a married woman
that you can't be with. So at that time, all right, look
what happened, this happened to a modest daughter of a king, קל
וחומר kal v’chomer to anyone, that's it, no more men and women
being alone, unmarried men and women being alone together. And just to
finish the משנה, mishnah, אדוניה בן חגית מתנשא לאמר אני אמלוך. Adoniya
ben Chagit mitnaseh l’emor ani emloch. So אדוניה also had a rebellion
and he said I'm going to be king. אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב מלמד שביקש
להולמו ולא הולמתו. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav melamed shebikash l’holmo v’lo
holmato. So he wanted to put the crown on him and he
tried to and it didn't fit. That's what that's about. ויעש לו
רכב ופרשים וחמשים איש רצים לפניו.
Vayahas lo rechev u’farashim
v’chamishim ish ratzim l’faniav. So he made a chariot and he had
fifty footmen in front of him to run ahead of him. אטו
כולהו, Atu kulhu, so what, a lot of the princelings have their
own entourage.
So אמר רב יהודה אמר רב כולם נטולי טחול וחקוקי כפות רגליים
היו. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav kulam ntulei tchol v’chakukei kipot raglayim
hayu. So they all were missing spleens, I guess that makes you
run faster, more durable somehow. And also like here it says,
וחקוקי כפות רגליים, v’chakukei kipot raglayim,
it was like carved, it says their soles were carved out. What
it basically means is deadened their nerves because people used to run
barefoot, so they're able to
run and go over thorns and thistles and not go ouch, ouch,
oh, ouch, so the nerve endings were dead so that they were
able to be especially fast and swift and go long distances. All
right, let's stop here.
Thank you
man. Welcome.